okay
so thanks everyone for joining tonight
um
if you can i would appreciate if you
could turn on your camera
um i'm viviane and i'm the vice
president of ams committee and tonight
we have a guest speaker
chris he's an sbu alum and
currently works as an actuarial
associate at prudential
before we get started this event is also
co-hosted by oas so
gloria if you want to give like a short
intro
yes hi everyone um i'm the president of
the
organization of actuarial students um
yeah nice to be here if anyone has any
questions about that as well you can
leave it in the
chat box and i think our
vice president and our treasurer are
here today as well
yeah okay thanks gloria so
i guess we can turn it over to chris if
you want to just like
kind of introduce yourself
thing all right um so my name is
christopher matthew
i graduated from stony brook as a double
major
in ams and economics back in 2019
uh before i continue can you guys hear
me
cool all right so um i graduated in 2019
and uh basically um
the the story of me becoming an actor
associate prudential is
it's kind of a it's kind of an up and
hill kind of thing
uh up and down kind of thing i should
say and really
um the way i like to put it was that i
kind of just
you know enrolled in college straight
out of high school i went to
private school all my life um so i
graduated from st john the baptist in
west islip
long island and that's pretty much where
um when i got into stony brook i
actually got in
um for a psychology major because i was
pretty convinced that i wanted to do
like something in the
in arts but it wasn't until my senior
year that i took an economics class and
i figured oh like
um i think money and managing money and
things like that i think that's a lot
more interesting
so when i first got into stony brook the
first thing i did was change my major
from
psychology to economics and i did like
economics
a lot of the courses were interesting i
thought that the
curriculum for um classes outside of
macromicro i mean those are your core
classes but
you have a lot of electives and things
like that and i thought those are pretty
interesting
but it got to a point where i felt like
i really wasn't building
a desirable skill set and that's
something i'll dig into
later but for the most part i
i just remember being a freshman in like
uh
like an upper division course because i
was able to get
out of a few like prerequisites um with
some ap
credits and i'm thinking this kind of no
way that like a freshman sophomore
should be
in an upper division class that kind of
just means that like
although i might be on pace to graduate
early i don't
feel like i'd be graduating with
something that's going to give me
you know an edge in the marketplace or
the job market
so um by my sophomore year i really just
tried to take more time to myself
and figure out what exactly my plan was
as to
what exactly i was going to do after i
graduated and
i had um all of my friends all my close
friends
um are all working on finance and each
one of them
is is doing something different now i
have one friend who's
also an actuarial analyst and he works
for new york life
and he was very much into his actuarial
track at
um st john's university i had another
friend at a
i'm sorry uh baruch baruch and he works
at aig
as a as an analyst and i have a third
friend who works not so much in finance
but he does work for jp morgan so
um as much of a flex as that is he works
in um computer science
so i'm thinking i have three friends
that are
working or are working towards at the
time
really like significant and and
fulfilling
uh types of careers and
i'm thinking wow like my best guess is
graduating from stony brook and possibly
trying to like work for
the fed but that really never happens
right like you you can't just
graduate with a bachelor's degree and
and expect
like to get this really high-paying job
unless you have some sort of
um skill set something that's going to
really
draw attention to you and make you stand
out from
the other thousands and thousands of
people who are graduating with similar
degrees
so um i asked my friend um the one at
st john's university about his um
actual science courses and he was more
than happy to to tell me about it
and i did find that um a lot of what he
was saying were things that i
found more um interesting to me at least
based on the economics courses that i
took there was some
like this there's a probability exam and
um
in the exam track for for becoming an
actuary there was
a finance exam or an early like
financial mathematics exam
and i thought that those were um
those those types of classes really do
lead to skill sets that are more
desirable
in a job market and so
um i kind of just said what the heck
like you know i'll try one of these
exams i was a little cocky at the time
um i thought if he could do it anybody
else like you know i could walk into
this and
barely have to study and and take an
exam and it wasn't so much until my
junior year of college i actually sat
for one of these things
and um i failed my first sitting after
studying for eight months
so that was that was a an eye-opening
experience for me
but um around the same time i was
i was lucky enough to at least um hang
around my friends close enough to
to hear about these career fairs and
there's this one that
that used to happen annually in the city
um it's hosted by um an organization
called
um azny the the it's an acronym for
something
much more longer than that but basically
they hold a career
fair in the city every single year um i
think it's actually two but the bigger
one is in
in the fall and um i was able to get in
touch with a recruiter at
massmutual who kind of liked um what i
had to say and and
basically gave me an opportunity to
intern
um at massmutual in the summer of 2018.
so
um that in itself
plus the the um opportunity to take the
exam
i did fail it the first time but i
passed it the second time
that in itself was was able to to to
give me
um some somewhat of a leverage and
somewhat of a confidence into
deciding that actuary of science is
something that i wanted to do
um after i graduated from stony brook
and so i kind of really just stuck with
that track i finished my internship
um and once i had my internship and i'll
talk more about it later but once i had
my internship
i felt that i had a lot more direction
in the coursework that i felt like was
missing um
because i i do feel like if you're
trying to
get into an actuarial career path out of
an ams major
there are some classes that are going to
definitely relate to to the career path
and then there's a bunch of
electives and courses that you might not
really
find use for right and i'm talking about
certain classes like your finite maps
or your differential
equations things like that um i feel
like
certain courses like your your
multivariate calculus that's definitely
going to help you when you take certain
exams
others not so much but after you have an
internship
you'll probably for the first time see
some of the the missing skill sets and
the missing
knowledge that that you you currently
have at that point in time
and you'll be able to take the classes
that will um
give you that knowledge that will that
will supply you with those skill sets so
that you can become
a better overall candidate so that's
what i was able to do
my senior year i graduated um didn't
have a job offer in my hand at the time
but
i was more than confident that i was
very much on track for one
really it just takes a matter of having
a well-built enough resume to to be able
to
keep up and to draw attention of
recruiters
because a lot of the times when you are
applying for a job you're going against
um other candidates and other students
from
ivy league schools or target schools um
target schools being like um
i'm going to just shadow um umass and
and yukon those are schools that
um have dedicated actuarial programs
which is something that stony brook does
not have so
um in order to put yourself on the radar
you're going to need to have
multiple exams maybe one or two even
three
um you're gonna have to need rev
relevant coursework and
possibly a few internship or at least
leadership experiences
so if you're um essentially
like volunteering at the career center
or if you are um leader
like you hold a leadership position in a
club um
then that's something that's going to
help fill out your resume and help you
stand out as opposed to
other candidates who probably are
passing exams too
probably go to a target school but
just for the matter of fact you just
aren't doing as much as you are
um right because you have to really sit
down and think everybody's got the same
24 hours
and if you can prove that you're you're
more efficient you're able to do more in
that 24 hours
on a consistent basis that's what's
going to
allow a recruiter to see the value in
having you work for their organization
but um back to the point um i was
lucky enough to to um
interview with prudential and a few
other insurance companies
and it just so happened that um
prudential which
i'll be very honest when i was looking
for career
opportunities i everyone has a list
by the time that they're ready to apply
for jobs and a lot of people really want
something that's relatively closer so if
you're from new york you want a job in
new york if you're from massachusetts
you want
you know you know you want to work at
massmutual or something
um i got the job in jersey um those guys
really liked me
i liked the people that i interviewed
there and i kind of just said
what the heck you know i could move i
can get an apartment
out in new jersey and that's that's
something that you should also really
consider
when you're looking for your first
actual position you don't want to be
picky
with the opportunities that come your
way if it's an opportunity for you to
learn
and you feel like you can like at least
like at minimum
leverage that opportunity to find a
better opportunity in the future
then you should by all means consider it
but um you know to get back to the point
that's really how i i wound up
at prudential um and before i continue
um maybe i'll just take a second to hear
some questions and
maybe answer some questions like i said
i'm kind of dealing
with like a completely different setup i
did have a presentation
i swear this was supposed to go a lot
more smoothly but you know
here i am this is your chance to talk to
a person who's
kind of just been through what you guys
are about to go through
and i'm trying to keep this as authentic
as possible clearly it's not formal
um so by all means like you know if you
got
any questions please just announce
yourself name
graduating year question let's hear it
if anyone has any questions they can
feel free to unmute
if not there are some people that
submitted questions
and then we can go through those
um i have a question um so
you said you came in as a psych major
and then you like transferred into like
the actuarial world
so what was the learning curve like for
you
well to be fair i never
really took um a psychology course
when i got to stony brook the the first
thing that i did
um like literally the week of
orientation
i switched out of psychology into
economics
but to answer your question there still
was a very significant learning curve in
becoming just an economics major
um and and and learning and picking up
the the math classes that you're going
to take as an ams major
because there's a lot of um coursework
and economics that
might take like a little you know a baby
derivative or a baby integral
but you're not going to have the skill
set that you need the
the knowledge that you require to um
to take on actuary exams which are very
quantitative and
are going to require that you are not
only taking
certain ams courses like certain
calculus courses
but excelling at them like you really
have to be able to
um convince yourself that you truly
understand
the very fundamentals of calculus
because you're going to take those
fundamentals and apply it to a
completely different subject right
um but there is a learning curve um and
if i can even extend
off of that there's a learning curve
even beyond the courses that you're
going to take at stony brook
you're going to have to you're going to
have to basically
um understand that the courses at stony
brook by themselves
are not enough um for any for any
significant
um role out there any significant um
quantitative role especially so if you
want to be
an actuary or if you want to be
let's say a trader or
an underwriter the skills that you pick
up at stony brook
um or at least the courses in sony room
most of them are teaching theory
you need to learn application you need
to learn excel you need to learn
coding languages um you don't have to be
terribly proficient at them
but you need to be able to pick up a
spreadsheet that your manager is giving
you
um and and be able to manipulate it
because for the most part
especially when you're at my level um
that's what you're going to be doing
you're you're not going to be building
models from scratch you're not going to
be
um you know reinventing the wheel or
anything you're going to take
some project or some report or some
database
that was given to you and essentially
you're going to have to
um to to continue working on it
um you're going to have to perform extra
analysis on it things of that nature
okay got it thanks so much for answering
the question i also have another
question
um so how much like programming and like
since you're constantly doing with
databases and since a lot of things are
automated nowadays
like how much programming do you do is
it just like basically like vba
and like r or does it like vary per
position
it definitely varies my position
um see like me in in my current role i'm
in a pricing role and i would say that
pricing
is probably one of your more common
roles and
for the most part unless you're really
working in a very niche
product line or a very niche department
you're not going to be programming very
much um pricing is more of like a
it's more of just a data analysis type
of role where you're
constantly taking in um external factors
um new assumptions and things of that
nature and you're plugging them into a
model
and then the model is going to spit out
results and you're basically going to
have to understand them
and that takes more of a deductive skill
set than a programming skill set
but if you're more um inclined to
coding or to programming then i would
suggest that when you're looking for
internships when you're looking for
full-time roles
you specifically ask for modeling um
roles because modeling is really
the there there are actuaries who
literally sit and model
and code and put together new models
for products that are up and coming
right so if like
um i don't know let's say tia bank
was trying to come up with a new annuity
product and
or a new like say retirement product and
there was no current model for it
and they needed a bunch of actuaries to
to come together
and code this this new model by
examining another product that maybe
some other company
is selling and taking that and
converting it maybe from
python to r if that's your kind of thing
then you definitely want to ask for a
modeling
um otherwise not there's not really much
of a
of a push for actuaries to
code maybe like a little bit to to
maybe a little bit in um sql
but that's more of like a database type
of uh
application of coding or programming so
um to
put it simple uh you're not really
programming you're not really coding
as an actuary unless you are in
one of like maybe three roles that
really call for it
okay god thank you so much
hello
i was actually just wondering um
if you had a preference for um
health and um life insurance
or if you were just applying to anything
um see what you get or property and
casualty
because i've heard like people who have
like preferences or people who've just
applied
to everything and just see what they get
and the first thing they got they just
stuck with so
that that is something that i really
wanted to cover
um in the presentation i had prepared um
what you're saying is definitely very
relevant
in finding a job it shapes your attitude
in how you go about finding a job as in
applying to everything or applying to
specific roles
and it also will affect your
conversations recruit
recruiters i think it's better if you
you know if you research and if you
if you talk to other people and try to
just
pick something so that at least you have
something to say to a recruiter because
if i'm a recruiter and you come to me
and you might have one exam
and you know you think you want to be an
actuary but you come to me and you say
oh i'm i'm just looking for anything i'm
not really like
you you're basically telling me you
didn't even try like you didn't even
like research
you don't even know what types of roles
or departments there are
so um for me granted i was looking at
like
maybe life insurance and somehow wound
up in retirement which is very different
but um i think it definitely
brings more power to you um in the
conversation
when you walk up to a recruiter and say
hey i want a pricing role
in an annuity product or hey i want a
modeling role and a new
product um if you're able to walk up to
um let's say a recruiter at the astony
fair
say that as opposed to oh like i'm just
looking for whatever
like that's going to impress him a lot
more because
i guarantee you 50 students are going to
walk up to them
48 are going to say i'm looking for
whatever and the two that they remember
are going to be the people who came in
there with straight up demand saying
yo i want evaluation wrong or i want
that pricing rule
um so to answer your question preference
maybe in your head like keep it in your
head um
and just know who you're talking to
right like just just
you know if you're going to um like
prudential credentials retirement
uh department is huge there's tons of
role like jobs in the retirement
department but if you go to like let's
say
massmutual it might not be as big um so
you also have to study like what is that
insurance company selling like what's
their what's their big thing
like and if you can kind of like you
know maybe
right keep a list somewhere and say okay
mass mutual is really big in annuities
new york life is really big in life
insurance um
then when you talk to a new york life
recruiter then you go up to that new
york life recruiter and say
oh um i was wondering if you had any
roles in your annuity department or
term life department but uh yeah that's
my answer sorry i was so long-winded
no problem
any other questions or um
hi chris what's up uh thank you again
for doing this q a
um my name is keeshan i'm currently a
chemical engineering and
applied mathematics major and i'll be
graduating in 2022
but i'll be graduating grad school here
at 2023
um so my main question for you is what
advice
would you give an inspiring actuary
for landing his first or her first
internship
i know you mentioned the career fair but
what else would you recommend
um so i think when it comes down to it
landing a role
really is a mix of your attitude
and also what you've done to
prove that you are ahead of the
competition because
just like you know it's not unique to
actuary science everything that you
apply to out there
is competitive there's always going to
be hundreds of people
from i hate to say hundreds of people
with similar degrees from probably even
more renowned
you know colleges and universities and
so
um if you have at least something
that you can totally bank on like for me
when i was applying rose i was
volunteering a lot i volunteered for
this
um one organization that was working
with microsoft so i actually got to go
to microsoft
i actually like hosted career fairs at
microsoft
and for me that was something that i
could bank on
would catch any recruiters interest if i
was to
just passively mention it right and i
wouldn't even need to like
you know overdo it on my resume i feel
like for the most part
when you're applying your jobs
everyone's resume is gonna say this uh
look the same basically it's gonna have
one or two exams at the top
it's gonna have you know classes that
you took your major ams this and that
but what's gonna set you apart are the
things that
not everyone else is doing so the things
that really make you unique
um so if you have that and if you have
the right attitude as in
you're going to keep applying um if an
interview process
doesn't really work out well or maybe
recruiters aren't reaching back out to
you like fast enough
because i'm not gonna lie you might
reply um apply to a company
and they won't get back to you for like
two three months and that happened to me
um it's happened to my friends and it's
just
part of the corporate world that um
college students
really aren't warned about before they
graduate but
it's it's it's kind of you know it's
kind of a grind
where you're just going to be consistent
you're going to be level-headed
and no matter how you're feeling even on
your worst day you're going to show
people the best side of yourself
and if you can do that consistently i
promise you
someone is going to pick you up someone
is going to give you that opportunity
to interview and you you just got to be
yourself you just got to be
um you know there's this is a field
where
a lot of people think that you have to
be perfect
to get into it um it's really not like
that there's
tons of people who
you know they don't have the 4.0 or they
don't have
six exams when they graduate and that's
okay because if you can kind of
demonstrate
that you're willing to learn and that
you're willing to
um place yourself outside of your
comfort zone
um and i'm i'm saying that you're
demonstrating this without even saying
it you're demonstrating it
just by talking about the other things
that you do
um then then i promise you you will get
interviews and someone will pick you up
and it'll
literally be a matter of time before
you're in a role yourself
so that's my advice thank you so much
no problem hey chris
i'm joe i'm a sophomore right
right now so you mentioned before that
leadership roles are important to stand
out to recruiters
i was wondering what leadership
experiences you had
before you landed your first job or
internship
right so um i did mention it a little
bit before
um i volunteered for um
well i'll start i'll start small
actually
i was uh
i did spend some time with the organic
organization of actuary students
um not only was i in the club but my
senior year i decided to be
their um pr manager or you know there's
a specific name for the role but
basically my job
was to try and get people to come to her
club so
i tried um to to push all of these
initiatives to the president and the
vice president and
and um our treasurer to to try and
find new ways to to get people to come
to our club
um because i felt like acura science is
kind of a very niche group
at stony brook there's no program there
and you you really have like a subset
of ams majors who really like even know
about it
so my thing was um if if we could get
more people to come in even if we offer
like pizza or something
and if we can like kind of uh create
like more interesting meetings like
we have like these uh coding sessions
and stuff like that
instead of like you know instead of like
having a powerpoint presentation and
just reading off of that
why don't we do something interactive um
that was totally my game and
that's something that we were able to to
start implementing that senior year i
don't know if it really carried through
after i graduated but just being able to
to do that um first of all it gave me
a lot of good experience and kind of
just being comfortable talking to people
because i did go into classrooms and i
did announce that we were having
meetings
and i'm not really um the most gifted
speaker
it's probably obvious by now but things
like that will force you
to kind of just get over it and and just
come out of your shell and it'll give
you experience that you desperately need
when you're trying to get into a
professional world so that's one thing
that's one leadership
uh position that i had another was um
for an organization called the selective
corporate internship program um
aka skip and this is the program that
was teamed up with microsoft
and basically what their program was was
it was multi-dimensional they had an
internship program over the summer
and really was just a career development
program but
what they also did throughout the year
is that they hosted fairs they hosted
um demos and they hosted a whole bunch
of things where students were invited to
come to microsoft
and they were able to sit with actual
representatives from
a whole bunch of different companies
like i'm talking b and y melon
i'm talking um they they actually did
have prudential there
but it's not really how i met prudential
and um
you know this was a really cool
opportunity for me to
to demonstrate leadership because i was
able
to to help um organize some of these
career fairs and organize some of these
meetings and
and other things and that just like the
the role that i had
in the actuarial club um gave me
opportunity to really like you know just
talk to people get to know people
um every time i met a recruiter it
wasn't even a matter of like trying to
pitch myself or anything like that it
was really just
you know you'll be surprised how far you
can go
in a conversation with someone when you
genuinely just ask how their day is or
you know how they're doing um not
everything
outside of like getting a job is you
know
shoving resumes in people's faces and
trying to tell people you want to be
this and and that like it's not really
always about that sometimes just being a
human being
will will put you in places that you
really never thought you could be and
it's really just
you striving to be a better person so
um leadership roles hands down will make
you unique
those are the things that you would
really talk about and like i said before
when you have leadership roles
um plural you don't need to describe
everything in your resume in fact you
know the best advice i can give
all of you right now is that your resume
is just
there it's just slices of who you are
it's not
exactly all of who you are um
never put everything on your resume it's
kind of like showing your cards in a
poker match
right you want to have something
to really be able to express to anybody
um different things right depending on
who you talk to depending on the context
you want to have stories and you want to
have experiences that you can kind of
just
talk about and and and just like you
know you're not you're not being
you know pretentious or anything about
it you just you're just saying like oh
yeah i volunteered for
ex group at my school or
you know i volunteer at the church once
in a blue moon that's how i pass the
time and
um if you're able to do that then you
will like
acquire more and more interest um and
people will remember you
right it's a real it's always a good
thing when at the end of the career fair
you
can you make like that weird eye contact
with that person and they still remember
who you are if they don't remember who
you are
then you aren't memorable so that's my
advice
thanks i appreciate that and thanks for
coming out talking to us
no problem hi chris my name is sonia
i'm a junior right now and my expected
graduation date
is um it's early i plan to graduate next
semester so my graduation will be in
december
do you think that will like hinder me at
all and landing a full-time offer
like right now i do have an internship
lined up for this summer and obviously
you hope that they extend you a
full-time offer but
if that doesn't happen is uh recruiting
on the off cycle
any like harder you would think do you
think
well you see i've been told that um as
in
i've been told to i've actually been
told to graduate
later than i needed to because
i didn't have an offer a full-time offer
the day that i graduated
and that was nerve-wracking because what
you will
find in actuary science and literally
any other field in finance is that
there's going to be people who have
in like offers in their hand and when
you
have friends or you know people that
have those offers in their hands and you
don't have one
that's the most nerve-wracking thing
ever and you start to think oh what's
wrong with me and
and things like that really it's nothing
wrong with you
and you know to really um explicitly
answer your question
you'll be fine as long as you're
consistently applying
um literally you know recruiters are
looking for people
all year long i mean i was getting a
phone call from
some recruiter at selby jennings and i'm
thinking
it's march i thought the season was over
but apparently it's not um and quite
frankly i'm pretty happy where i am so i
didn't pick up the phone
but but recruiters are always looking
for jobs and now
um you know i know that things got weird
with with cobra and everyone working
remotely
and stuff but if anything that changed
the game
because things used to be very cyclical
but now that there are remote positions
being offered all over the place
there are offers being made to people
year round now like it's ridiculous like
they're they will just start looking for
people in may
and they weren't doing that before you
know what i mean but but
but now like now is an opportunity
where companies are actually trying to
to increase the size of their their base
because
it's a lot cheaper to hire people now
they don't gotta hold like uh
they don't have to give you your own
cubicle or something like that like you
can actually work from home
or you might have like this weird free
addressing thing where
you're in the office a few days a week
and then you're home
um but don't get discouraged um it
doesn't really matter when you graduate
as long as you have a good resume and
you have
all of the other things i was talking
about earlier in this meeting you'll be
fine
trust me thank you
no prob we actually have a question in
the chat
um do you think gaining professional
experience in a similar field or
spending time passing more exams would
be more helpful in landing your first
role
that's a good one so
you want to balance you definitely want
to balance
um here's my critique on the exams
you definitely want to have one two
maybe even three just to prove that you
can pass them
um after three it's like
from a recruiter's perspective from
anyone's perspective it's like
we get it bro you can pass exams um what
else can you offer what else have you
done like what else like
who are you and you can't really
you can't really answer that who are you
question with just exams
you know what i mean like when you pass
exams
you'll find that the first thing that
they release is a candidate number
um and the reason that i'm saying that
is because it's very literal you are
just a number of thousands hundreds of
thousands of people who have passed this
exam
yes it's an accomplishment yes you're
doing something that
very few people in the world can do but
it's not all of who you are so um you
know
i think the best way to answer that is
that it depends
if you have no exams definitely like
you know you want to get it together and
get one or two exams but once you have
those two exams maybe even three
you really want to dedicate whatever you
got left um because i would argue you'd
be at the end of college by the time you
have three exams you want to dedicate
that to
leadership roles because the leadership
roles are where you're going to talk
about
the exams i promise you if you
go to a recruiter and the first thing
you say is i passed p
they're gonna say okay good for you so
did everyone else here
like but if you have like a story
especially if you have a sense of humor
if you have a sense of humor um and i'm
i'm saying that's that's very
it's it's very subjective but i'm saying
if you
are the type of person who can just
literally walk up to anyone
and and just like engage them in
conversation whether it's through humor
whether it's through just
pure like interest that is what's going
to get you a job
way faster than some kid who probably
has like six exams up his belt like it's
it it doesn't really you know make you a
better person for having
more exams per se right you're
you're just basically saying like i
dedicated more time than i needed to
passing exams
like so that's that's the answer to
that question um it depends get your two
exams first that's that's my advice to
all
of you
any other questions i have a question
so i am graduating also next semester
december 2021
i was just wondering like what was your
job hunting process like like
how many jobs did you apply to like how
many responses
did you get like on average like how
many interviews did you do and i know
for
actuarial interviews sometimes they'll
ask you like a weird question like
how many chairs are in a building or
like i got one that was like
how can you estimate how many trees are
in central park
so like how did you prepare for those
kind of questions
and answer them okay
so all right this discussion has
multiple parts let's see
so the job searching process
was i want to say it was
it felt like torture but it's it's very
it depends on your attitude in one flip
of a second that torture
could literally just scream opportunity
um because even though like i didn't get
like a million job offers out the door
and some people just never responded
some companies got back to me literally
months after i signed
prudential you have to adjust your
attitude
so that you are happy with the fact that
at least
you are in the position to be able to
apply
that is way farther than you just
started college or
you just graduated college and now you
decided you want to be an actuary
um then i'm not saying it's too late for
anyone i'm just saying
that you have to take everything with
a grain of salt you have to sit down and
say
i'm blessed that i have the guts to
apply to
my dream job right now because some
people don't some people
never like really have the confidence to
do that
um and so you know you're you're also
going to have to have like a
thick skin because like i said it's
going to take a while to get responses
it's going to take um you know
quite some time for you to really
perfect your resume perfect your pitches
perfect even your cover letters um best
advice i can give you
is be consistent um
don't be picky like i said if you have
to apply to a few companies like let's
say
i don't know the hartford or something
like that just apply to them
and if they reach out to you like i want
to say waste their time
but maybe your attitude will change if
you actually get a call back from
someone and like the next week you
actually get a call back from a company
you really did want to work for
so justify everywhere you know what i
mean it's kind of a numbers game
um you definitely want to apply in the
track that you're taking exams in so if
you're soa if you're life and health
apply for life and health companies
please don't apply to like
travelers because if you apply to
travelers and you tell them that you're
taking out
town they're gonna they're gonna
basically i hate to say they're gonna
probably like curse you out and never
they're gonna put you on a block list
because
you're definitely not helping
anyone by applying to a job that you
literally wouldn't even qualify for
right so um yeah so to
answer that question i i just say be
consistent keep applying
don't be picky and um take everything
with a grain of salt
and to answer your second question
there's some there's there's some
questions that you will
find in in interviews and it really just
depends on
the team uh the company the organization
that you're applying to
for example i had two interviews at
prudential
the first one went terribly wrong um
i was applying into a pension risk
transfer
department and i'll never forget the
question
he this uh this manager high-level
manager
um well it's funny i was supposed to
interview one person
because the lead manager was out on
vacation
it turned out the day that they called
me um i was expecting the person that
was listed in the email but
like when they picked up or when they
called me they were like oh yeah
i'm the actual manager i'm back from
vacation early
and i'm thinking oh crap hey
like it's not that big of a deal because
i didn't know him anyway but like you
know just those little things can happen
in
interview like opportunities so you just
got to be aware of it
but the question that he asked me was
what are our two biggest risks
and let me tell you that was
the biggest choke i've ever had in my
entire life i
i answered one of them i answered one of
them
i said uh interest rate risk
oh what's going on
uh did my camera just cut out or yeah
we can still hear you though okay all
right fine
um so so
basically um he asked me to
uh he asked me what the two biggest
risks were i got interest rate risk
the other risk was something that i just
could not i was reaching for it but i
just could not get it
and only after let's say a minute a full
minute of silence
um he kind of just said you know let me
put this kid out of his misery
and he answered it for me and i was just
kind of dumbfounded
and it was really just one of those
experiences where
um you know i i sti i think i handed it
with grace but like i still
you know felt like i wasn't getting a
job after that right because if some
if the next person that was interviewed
answered it he'd be one
half step better or further than i was
so um you know that's going to happen
sometimes you're actually going to get
all the way to the interview process
and then all of a sudden
um you know it's not going well and
that's okay
that's why it's a numbers game and you
have to learn
from your mistakes um
the second interview obviously went a
lot better than the first
but it was a for a completely different
team and i thought the questions that i
was being asked were
actually you know they're the type of
questions
or they were the type of questions that
um
were perfectly like asked
in a sense where i had just finished
taking an exam
um that taught me the the fundamentals
that was being asked in this interview i
was being asked about
portfolio duration and things like that
and that's something you learned about
in
the second actuary exam fm and um
you know it just it just went a lot
better for me that time
but you're gonna have to basically just
you know take on as many like
interviews as you can um
never say no to one even if you don't
want to do it even if you really don't
want to
work for the company per se if you have
an
opportunity to interview you take it
because that experience is something
that
you can take forward into your next um
interview experience
so yeah that's i i hope that answered
your question vivian
yeah definitely thank you no problem
we probably have time for like one more
question
oh you can't figure it out
um i can ask one from like the questions
that people submitted sure
oh what's the biggest difference between
the expectation and reality
of an actuarial career okay all right
so
i don't know what you guys think an
actuary does at this point in time
that's probably why we're in this q a to
begin with
but um a lot of people think being an
actuary is like this
super quantitative role where you're
using like
the finest like mathematics to answer
very complex
questions and things like that and to an
extent
yes but like the reality is that
a lot of junior actuarial roles are
really just more or less like a very
fancy like uh um
like uh data analysis where you're
basically just playing around in excel
but you're basically just playing around
in something that your manager put
together
and you gotta summarize some information
and give
you know send it back to them so that he
could forward it up the uh
up the ladder so for the most part early
in actuary science
um i wouldn't say there's a difference
between being an actuary and being
you know a finance role or something
like that or an underwriting role or
anything else in a insurance company
but uh as you move up your questions in
a way that you handle
um problems like business problems
becomes more high level
and so um actuaries typically will be
very we we like to use the terms in the
weeds where you're basically
like an uncharted territory nobody likes
to play around in the models
nobody likes to play around with all
those crazy numbers like spreadsheets
like
full and full and full of information um
your managers don't want to do it
that's why they make you do it so
as you move up um you will be that
manager who's
basically overseeing a junior um
actuary and in the same work that you
were doing not too long ago
but at that point you'll have a greater
understanding of it
um because whereas the the junior
actuary might be
putting together all this information
right they might not necessarily know
what you know what to do with it as in
why is this calculation why is this
information
important and that's that's the part
about being an
actuary that's very um unique you
are basically seeing very different
parts
of a product line or process
at varying points in your career by the
time you get to a vp
you don't care about anything except
that last bottom line number so whereas
it took somebody two weeks to finally
get it
you only care about that one number so
you could just drop it into a little you
know
um like uh let's say a financial
statement or something like that
and then you can be on your merry way
and everyone gets their bonuses and
everything's good so um you know
being an actuary is a lot like other
jobs but
if i could say there's a difference
or whether it's the difference it's very
much bent on integrity
it's very much bent on consistency
actuaries are held to
a higher standard than most other roles
you guys basically are the police of
your company
sometimes actuaries are viewed as the
sticklers because let's say your company
wants to
you know start selling a very risky
product well it's
actually his job so do all the math to
really go back to management and say
hey by selling this product we'd be
taking on more risk than we really want
so you know there's a lot of dimensions
to being an actuary
but um one thing i can really argue
is that it's it definitely
is a very niche role and
it might not be the thing for you if
you're not really bent on more
regulatory
um like processes right like filing and
things like that i think a lot of very
close um
and just in roles that are just as
prestigious
but also like well-paying and rewarding
are like data analysts
business analysts data scientists
each one of those jobs does something
different and
i think that at the end of the day
being an actuary is you know being an
actuary
is for you if you've done an internship
or two
and you really liked it um until you've
actually done that you can't really
you know say that it's it's the job for
you until
you know you've done it so
hope that answers the question yeah
definitely
well it's eight now so i guess we could
start closing but thanks so much for
being here
despite all the technical difficulties
i'm glad you made it and we didn't have
to like post for the meeting or anything
um i feel like you gave a lot of advice
that i haven't heard before
like not your conventional advice and
more of like shifting your mindset into
like a more
positive aspect and kind of like
seeing things in a different perspective
so i really enjoyed it
um i'm just gonna put your linkedin in
the chat in case anyone
wants to reach out to you or ask any
other questions
um you can connect with him on linkedin
there's also a
link to our website we have
a data analyst from disney coming in on
thursday march
25th and that event will also be
starting at 7pm
and then two weeks after that on april
8th we have a business performance
analyst from facebook coming in
um and you can find all of this on our
website and also join our mailing list
so if you think being an actuary isn't
for you maybe you want to go to those
events and hear
about what they would have to say um and
thanks so much again chris for speaking
tonight
thanks for having me yes i hope everyone
has a good night